Is E.T. out there?
هل توجد كائنات غير أرضيّة في مكان ما هناك؟
Well, I work at the SETI Institute.
حسنا، أعمل في معهد البحث عن مخلوقات ذكية غير أرضية (SETI).
That's almost my name. SETI:
وهذا تقريبا اسمي. (SETI):
Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence.
البحث عن مخلوقات ذكية غير أرضيّة.
In other words, I look for aliens,
وبكلمات أخرى، أنا أبحث عن الفضائييّن.
and when I tell people that at a cocktail party, they usually
وعندما أخبر الآخرين بذلك في حفلات الكوكتيل، عادة ما
look at me with a mildly incredulous look on their face.
ينظرون إليّ والارتياب على وجوههم.
I try to keep my own face somewhat dispassionate.
وأحاول أن أحافظ على وجه لا مبال بعض الشيء.
Now, a lot of people think that this is kind of idealistic,
الآن، يظن الكثيرون أن هذه الفكرة حالمة،
ridiculous, maybe even hopeless,
وسخيفة، وربّما حتى يائسة،
but I just want to talk to you a little bit about why I think
ولكني أرغب في الحديث قليلا عما يجعلني أعتقد
that the job I have is actually a privilege, okay,
أن هذه الوظيفة هي في واقع الأمر امتياز، حسنا،
and give you a little bit of the motivation for my getting into
وأخبركم حول ما ألهمني
this line of work, if that's what you call it.
لأقوم بعملي هذا.
This thing — whoops, can we go back?
هذا الأمر -- أوبس، هل يمكننا العودة
Hello, come in, Earth.
مرحبا، اجيبي ايتها الارض
There we go. All right.
ها نحن ذا ، حسناً
This is the Owens Valley Radio Observatory
هذا هو مرصد راديو اوينز فالي
behind the Sierra Nevadas, and in 1968,
خلف جبال سييرا نيفادا، و في عام 1968
I was working there collecting data for my thesis.
كنت اعمل هناك اجمع بعض المعلومات لأطروحة
Now, it's kinda lonely, it's kinda tedious, just collecting data,
كنت وحيدا و كان الوضع مملاً ، فقط اقوم بجمع المعلومات
so I would amuse myself by taking photos at night
لذا كنت اسلي نفسي بالتقاط الصور في الليل
of the telescopes or even of myself,
اصور التلسكوب او احياناً اصور نفسي
because, you know, at night, I would be the only hominid
لانه ، كما تعلمون ، في الليل ، اكون الانسان الوحيد
within about 30 miles.
في مساحة 30 ميل
So here are pictures of myself.
هذه صور التقطتها لنفسي
The observatory had just acquired a new book,
كان المرصد قد حاز على كتاب جديد
written by a Russian cosmologist
كتبه عالم كونيات روسي
by the name of Joseph Shklovsky, and then expanded
اسمه جوزيف شلافسكي ، ثم انتشر الكتاب
and translated and edited by a little-known
و ترجم و تم تعديله بواسطة شخص غير معروف نسبيا
Cornell astronomer by the name of Carl Sagan.
جنرال في علم الفلك اسمه كارل سيغان
And I remember reading that book,
و اتذكر انني قرأت ذلك الكتاب
and at 3 in the morning I was reading this book
و في الثالثة صباحاً كنت اقرأ الكتاب
and it was explaining how the antennas I was using
و كان يشرح كيف ان الهوائيات التي استعملها
to measure the spins of galaxies could also be used
لقياس دوران المجرات بمكن ايضاً ان تستعمل
to communicate, to send bits of information
للاتصال ، و ارسال أجزاء من المعلومات
from one star system to another.
من نظام نجمي الى الاخر
Now, at 3 o'clock in the morning when you're all alone,
الان ، الساعة الثالثة صباحاً و انت وحيد تماماً
haven't had much sleep, that was a very romantic idea,
و لم تحظ بالقدر الكافي من النوم ، كانت الفكره رومانسية للغاية
but it was that idea -- the fact that you could in fact
و لكن هذه الفكره ، حقيقة انك يمكن في ان
prove that there's somebody out there
تثبت انه يوجد شخص ما هناك
just using this same technology --
باستخدام نفس هذه التكنولوجيا
that appealed to me so much that 20 years later I took a job
قد اعجبتني للغاية ، مما جعلني اصبح موظفاً بعد 20 عاما
at the SETI Institute. Now, I have to say
في معهد SETI . الان يجب ان اقول
that my memory is notoriously porous, and I've often
انني معروف بذاكرتي الضعيفة ، و انني غالباً
wondered whether there was any truth in this story,
ما اتسائل ان كان هناك اي صحة لتلك القصة
or I was just, you know, misremembering something,
ام هل كنت ، فقط اعتقد انني اتذكر شيءً ما
but I recently just blew up this old negative of mine,
فقمت مؤخراً بتكبير اكدى صوري السالبة
and sure enough, there you can see
و بالتأكيد ، يمكنكم ان تروا هناك
the Shklovsky and Sagan book underneath that
كتابي شلوفسكي و سيغان تحت
analog calculating device.
هذه الالة الحاسبة التناظرية
So it was true.
اذا ، فكل هذا حقيقي.
All right. Now, the idea for doing this, it wasn't very old
حسناً . الان ، فكرة تنفيذ هذا المبدأ لم تكن قديمة
at the time that I made that photo.
و في الوقت الذي التقطت فيه هذه الصورة
The idea dates from 1960, when a young astronomer
بدأت الفكره في عام 1960 ، عندما قام رائد فضاء شاب
by the name of Frank Drake used this antenna
اسمه فرانك دريك باستعمال هذه الهوائيات
in West Virginia, pointed it at a couple of nearby stars
في غرب فرجينيا . وجهها الى بعض النجوم القريبة
in the hopes of eavesdropping on E.T.
على امل ان يتصنت على مخلوقات فضائية
Now, Frank didn't hear anything.
لم يسمع فرانك اي شيء
Actually he did, but it turned out to be the U.S. Air Force,
في الحقيقه لقد فعل ، و لكن اتضح انه صوت سلاح الجو الامريكي
which doesn't count as extraterrestrial intelligence.
و الذي لا يحسب على انه مخلوقات ذكية غير ارضية
But Drake's idea here became very popular
و لكن فكره دريك اصبحت رائجة جدا
because it was very appealing — and I'll get back to that —
لانها فكرة جذابة - و سوف اعود لهذه النقطة مره اخرى-
and on the basis of this experiment, which didn't succeed,
و على اساس هذه التجربة ، و التي لم تنجح
we have been doing SETI ever since,
و نحن نقوم بالبحث عن مخلوقات فضائية منذ ذلك الحين
not continuously, but ever since.
ليس باستمرار و لكن منذ ذلك الوقت.
We still haven't heard anything.
و حتى الان لم نسمع اي شيء
In fact, we don't know about any life beyond Earth,
في الحقيقة ، نحن لا نعلم ان كانت هناك اي حياة خارج الارض
but I'm going to suggest to you that that's going to change
و لكن سوف اقترح ان هذا سوف يتغير قريبا جدا،
rather soon, and part of the reason, in fact,
و قريبا جداً في الحقيقة ، و جزء من السبب ، في الحقيقة
the majority of the reason why I think that's going to change
اغلب الاسباب التي تقودني للاعتقاد بان هذا سيتغير
is that the equipment's getting better.
هو ان الاجهزة اصبحت احدث و افضل
This is the Allen Telescope Array, about 350 miles
هذه مصفوفة تلسكوب الان ، حوالي 350 ميلا
from whatever seat you're in right now.
من اي مكان انت فيه الان
This is something that we're using today
هذا ما نستخدمه اليوم
to search for E.T., and the electronics have gotten
للبحث عن مخلوقات فضائية ، و اصبحت الالكترونيات
very much better too.
افضل كثيرا ايضاً
This is Frank Drake's electronics in 1960.
هذه الكترونيات فرانك ديريك عام 1960
This is the Allen Telescope Array electronics today.
و هذه الكترونيات مصفوفة تلسكوب الان اليوم
Some pundit with too much time on his hands
قام عالم يمتلك الكثير من وقت الفراغ
has reckoned that the new experiments are approximately
يعتقد ان التجارب الحديثة هي تقريبا
100 trillion times better than they were in 1960,
100 ترليون مره افضل مما كانت عليه عام 1960
100 trillion times better.
100 ترليون مره افضل
That's a degree of an improvement that would look good
هذه درجة من التحسن تبدو جيدة
on your report card, okay?
على تقريرك ، حسناً
But something that's not appreciated by the public is,
و لكن هناك شيء لا يستطيع عامة الناس تقديره
in fact, that the experiment continues to get better,
في الحقيقة ، ان التجارب في تحسن مستمر
and, consequently, tends to get faster.
و عليه ، فقد اصبحت اسرع
This is a little plot, and every time you show a plot,
هذه خريطة صغيرة ، و كل مره تعرض خريطة ما
you lose 10 percent of the audience.
تفقد 10% من الجمهور
I have 12 of these. (Laughter)
لدي اثنا عشر خريطة كهذه (ضحك)
But what I plotted here is just some metric
و لكن ما سردته في هذه الخريطة هو بعض القياسات المترية
that shows how fast we're searching.
التي توضح السرعة التي نبحث بها
In other words, we're looking for a needle in a haystack.
بمعنى اخر ، نحن نبحث عن ابره في كومه قش
We know how big the haystack is. It's the galaxy.
و نحن نعلم حجم كومة القش . انها المجرة
But we're going through the haystack no longer
و لكننا لم نعد نبحث في كومة القش
with a teaspoon but with a skip loader,
باستخدام ملعقة و لكن باستخدام حمّالة,
because of this increase in speed.
بسبب هذه الزيادة في السرعة
In fact, those of you who are still conscious
في الواقع، هؤلاء منكم الذين لا يزالون واعين
and mathematically competent,
و يستطيعون اجراء عمليات حسابية !
will note that this is a semi-log plot.
سيلاحظون ان هذه خريطة جرئية
In other words, the rate of increase is exponential.
بمعنى اخر ان معدل الزيادة أسي
It's exponentially improving. Now, exponential is an
انه يتحسن بمعدل اسي. الان، كلمة اسي هي
overworked word. You hear it on the media all the time.
كلمة مستهلكة، تسمعونها في الاعلام طوال الوقت
They don't really know what exponential means,
و لكنهم لا يعلمون ما ذا تعني كلمة اسي
but this is exponential.
و لكن هذه هو الاسي
In fact, it's doubling every 18 months, and, of course,
في الحقيقه هو يتضاعف كل 18 شهراً و بالطبع
every card-carrying member of the digerati knows
اي شخص يحمل بطاقة خبير في الحاسوب يعرف
that that's Moore's Law.
ان هذا اسمه قانون موور
So this means that over the course of the next
هذا يعني انه في الفترة القادمة
two dozen years, we'll be able to look at a million star systems,
من الاثنتي عشر عاما ، سوف نستطيع ان نرى ملايين الانظمة النجمية
a million star systems, looking for signals
مليون نظام نجمي ، بحثا عن اشارات
that would prove somebody's out there.
تثبت ان هناك شخصا ما هناك
Well, a million star systems, is that interesting?
حسناً، مليون نظام شمسي ، هل هذا مثير؟
I mean, how many of those star systems have planets?
اعني، كم من هذه الانظمة النجمية تحتوى على كواكب؟
And the facts are, we didn't know the answer to that
و الحقائق تقول، اننا لم نعرف الاجابة على هذا السؤال بعد
even as recently as 15 years ago, and in fact, we really
حتى بالعودة للخمسة عشر عاما الماضية ، في الحقيقة ، نحن حقا
didn't know it even as recently as six months ago.
لم نعرف حتى الستة اشهر الماضية
But now we do. Recent results suggest
و لكن الان نعلم. الدراسات الحديثة تقول
that virtually every star has planets, and more than one.
انه افتراضاً كل نجم لديه كواكب ، و اكثر من واحد
They're like, you know, kittens. You get a litter.
انها مثل، تعلمون، القطط ، لديك فضلات
You don't get one kitten. You get a bunch.
انت لا تجلب قطة واحدة بل تجلب العديد منها
So in fact, this is a pretty accurate estimate
لذا في الحقيقة، هذا تقدير دقيق جداً
of the number of planets in our galaxy,
عن عدد الكواكب في مجرتنا
just in our galaxy, by the way,
في مجرتنا فقط،و على فكرة
and I remind the non-astronomy majors among you
انا اذكر من هم بعيدون عن مجال الفلك بينكم
that our galaxy is only one of 100 billion
ان مجرتنا هي واحدة من بين 100 بليون مجرة
that we can see with our telescopes.
نستطيع ان نراها بواسطة التلسكوب
That's a lot of real estate, but of course,
هذا يساوي العديد من العقارات ،و لكن بالطبع
most of these planets are going to be kind of worthless,
معظم هذه الكواكب ستصبح تقريبا بلا قيمة
like, you know, Mercury, or Neptune.
مثل، كوكب عطارد او نيبتون
Neptune's probably not very big in your life.
كوكب نيبتون ليس كبيرا في حياتنا
So the question is, what fraction of these planets
و السؤال هو، ما النسبة من بين هذه الكواكب
are actually suitable for life?
التي تصلح فعلا للحياة؟
We don't know the answer to that either,
نحن لا نعلم الاجابة لهذا السؤال ايضاً
but we will learn that answer this year, thanks to
و لكننا سنعرف الاجابة هذه السنة ، و هذا بفضل
NASA's Kepler Space Telescope,
تلسكوب كبلر الفضائي التابع لناسا
and in fact, the smart money, which is to say the people who work on this project,
و في الحقيقة،الرهان الذكي، بالنسبة للاشخاص الذين يعملون في هذا الشروع
the smart money is suggesting that the fraction of planets
الرهان يميل الى ان نسبة الكواكب
that might be suitable for life is maybe one in a thousand,
التي يمكن ان تصلح للحياة يتوقع ان تكون واحد في الالف
one in a hundred, something like that.
واحد في المائة، شيء من هذا القبيل
Well, even taking the pessimistic estimate, that it's
و هذا اذا نظرنا الى اكثر التقديرات تفاؤلا
one in a thousand, that means that there are
واحد في الالف هذا يعني ان هناك
at least a billion cousins of the Earth
على الاقل بليون ابن عم لكوكب الارض
just in our own galaxy.
في مجرتنا وحدها.
Okay, now I've given you a lot of numbers here,
حسناً الان لقد اعطيتكم الكثير من الارقام هنا
but they're mostly big numbers, okay, so, you know,
و لكن اغلبها ارقام كبيره، حسنا ، اذا انتم تعلمون
keep that in mind. There's plenty of real estate,
احتفظو بهذه المعلومه. هناك الكثير من المباني السكنية
plenty of real estate in the universe,
الكثير من المساكن في الكون
and if we're the only bit of real estate in which there's
و لكن ان كنا نحن نمتلك المساكن الوحيدة التي تحتوي
some interesting occupants, that makes you a miracle,
على بعض السكان المثيرون للاهتمام، هذا يجعلنا معجزة
and I know you like to think you're a miracle,
و انتم تحبون ان تظنوا انكم معجزة
but if you do science, you learn rather quickly that
و لكن ان كنتم من عشاق العلم ستتعلمون بسرعة انه
every time you think you're a miracle, you're wrong,
كلما ظننا اننا معجزة تكتشف اننا مخطؤن
so probably not the case.
لذا غالبا ما لا تنطبق علينا هذه الحالة
All right, so the bottom line is this:
الخلاصة هي
Because of the increase in speed, and because of the
بسبب زيادة السرعة و بسبب
vast amount of habitable real estate in the cosmos, I figure
الاعداد الضخمة للأماكن المسكونة في الكون، اعتقد
we're going to pick up a signal within two dozen years.
اننا سوف نلتقط اشارة خلال ال24 سنة المقبلة
And I feel strongly enough about that to make a bet with you:
و انا اؤمن بشده بهذه النقطة لاقوم بالرهان عليها معك
Either we're going to find E.T. in the next two dozen years,
اما اننا سوف نجد مخلوقاً فضائياً خلال الـ24 سنة المقبلة
or I'll buy you a cup of coffee.
او سوف اشتري لك كوباً من القهوة.
So that's not so bad. I mean, even with two dozen years,
اذا، هذا ليس رهاناً سيئاً، اعني في الـ24 سنة
you open up your browser and there's news of a signal,
سوف تنظر في الاخبار و سوف تجد خبراً عن اشارة من الفضاء
or you get a cup of coffee.
او سوف تحظى بكوب من القهوة.
Now, let me tell you about some aspect of this that
الان، دعوني احدثكم عن بعض النواحي
people don't think about, and that is,
التي لا يفكر فيها الناس كثيراً، وهي
what happens? Suppose that what I say is true.
ماذا سيحدث؟ بافتراض ان كل ما قلته صحيح
I mean, who knows, but suppose it happens.
اعني، من يدري، و لكن لنفترض انه حصل.
Suppose some time in the next two dozen years
افترض انه في يوم ما في الـ 24 سنة القادمة
we pick up a faint line that tells us
التقطنا اشارة ضعيفة تخبرنا
we have some cosmic company.
انه لدينا صحبة في الكون
What is the effect? What's the consequence?
ما هو تأثير ذلك؟ ما هي النتائج المترتبه عليه؟
Now, I might be at ground zero for this.
الان، ربما اكون في قلب الحدث.
I happen to know what the consequence for me would be,
لانني اعرف ماهي النتائج المترتبة على هذا الاكتشاف
because we've had false alarms. This is 1997,
لاننا حظينا ببعض الاشارات الكاذبة من قبل. في العام 1997
and this is a photo I made at about 3 o'clock in the morning
هذه صورة التقطتها في الساعة الثالثة صباحاً
in Mountain View here, when we were watching
في منطقة ماونتن فيو، عندما كنا نراقب
the computer monitors because we had picked up a signal
شاشات الكمبيوتر لاننا كنا قد التقطنا اشارة
that we thought, "This is the real deal." All right?
كنا نظن انها الاشارة الحقيقية المنتظرة، حسناً؟
And I kept waiting for the Men in Black to show up. Right?
و كنت في انتظار الرجال ذوي البدلات السوداء ليظهروا.
I kept waiting for -- I kept waiting for my mom to call,
كنت انتظر... كنت انتظر اتصال و الدتي
somebody to call, the government to call. Nobody called.
اي شخص ما ليتصل، الحكومة. ولكن لم يتصل احد
Nobody called. I was so nervous
لم يتصل احد. كنت في غاية التوتر
that I couldn't sit down. I just wandered around
بحيث انني لم استطع الجلوس. فقط كنت اتحرك في المكان
taking photos like this one, just for something to do.
التقط الصور مثل هذه الصورة. فقط لاقوم بأي عمل ما
Well, at 9:30 in the morning, with my head down
حسناً في الساعة 9 و نصف صباحاً ، و كنت اضع رأسي
on my desk because I obviously hadn't slept all night,
على الطاولة لانني بالتأكيد لم استطيع ان انام طوال الليل
the phone rings and it's The New York Times.
رن جرس الهاتف، و كانت صحيف النيو يورك تايمز
And I think there's a lesson in that, and that lesson is
و فكرت ، يوجد درس ما هنا، و الدرس كان
that if we pick up a signal, the media, the media will be on it
انه اذا التقطنا اشارة ما، فإن الاعلام ، الاعلام سوف ينقض عليها
faster than a weasel on ball bearings. It's going to be fast.
اسرع من انقضاض ابن عرس على فريسة. سوف يكون الامر سريعاً.
You can be sure of that. No secrecy.
لك ان تتأكد تماما من هذا. لا يوجد مجال للسرية
That's what happens to me. It kind of ruins my whole week,
هذا ما حصل معي ، لقد تحطم اسبوعي كله
because whatever I've got planned that week is kind of out the window.
لأنه اياً كانت خططي لذلك الاسبوع فقد انتهت كلها
But what about you? What's it going to do to you?
و لكن ماذا عنك انت؟ كيف سيؤثر عليك انت؟
And the answer is that we don't know the answer.
و الاجابة هي اننا لا نعرف الاجابة
We don't know what that's going to do to you,
نحن لا نعرف كيف سيؤثر ذلك عليك
not in the long term, and not even very much in the short term.
ليس على المدى الطويل، و ليس كثيرا على المدى القريب
I mean, that would be a bit like
اعني، سيكون تقريبا كأنك
asking Chris Columbus in 1491, "Hey Chris,
تقول لكريستوفر كولمبوس عام 1491، هاي يا كريس
you know, what happens if it turns out that there's a
ماذا سيحدث اذا تبين انه هناك
continent between here and Japan, where you're sailing to,
قارة اخرى بين هذا المكان و اليابان، حيث انت تبحر
what will be the consequences for humanity
ماذا سيكون تأثير هذا الاكتشاف على البشرية
if that turns out to be the case?"
ان تبين ان هذه هي القضية؟
And I think Chris would probably offer you some answer
و اعتقد ان كريستوفر سوف يقوم بتزويدكم ببعض الاجابات
that you might not have understood, but it probably
التي ربما لن تفهموها، و لكنها في الغالب
wouldn't have been right, and I think that to predict
لن تكون صحيحة، و انا اعتقد ان التنبؤ
what finding E.T.'s going to mean,
بتأثير اكتشاف مخلوقات فضائية
we can't predict that either.
لا نستطيع ان نتوقع ذلك ايضاً
But here are a couple things I can say.
و لكن هذه بعض الاشياء التي استطيع ان اقولها
To begin with, it's going to be a society that's way in advance of our own.
في البداية، سوف يكون مجتمع متقدم جداً عن مجتمعنا
You're not going to hear from alien Neanderthals.
لن نسمع عن مخلوقات فضائية بدائية
They're not building transmitters.
و هم لا يبنون هوائيات
They're going to be ahead of us, maybe by a few thousand
سوف يكونون متقدمين عنا ، ربما بألاف السنوات
years, maybe by a few millions years, but substantially
و ربما بضعة ملايين السنين ، و لكن في الاساس
ahead of us, and that means, if you can understand
متقدمون عنا، و هذا يعني،ان كنت تستطيع ان تفهم
anything that they're going to say, then you might be able
كل ما يقولونه، اذا فانت قادر
to short-circuit history by getting information from a society
على ان تختصر التاريخ عن طريق اخذ معلومات من مجتمع
that's way beyond our own.
متقدم جدا عن مجتمعنا
Now, you might find that a bit hyperbolic, and maybe it is,
الان، قد تقول ان هذا الكلام مبالغ فيه، و ربما يكون كذلك
but nonetheless, it's conceivable that this will happen,
و لكن بغض النظر، فهو ايضا يمكن ان يحدث
and, you know, you could consider this like, I don't know,
و يمكنك ان تعتبر هذا مثل، لا اعرف
giving Julius Caesar English lessons and the key
اعطاي جوليوس سيزر دروس في اللغة الانجليزية و مفتاح
to the library of Congress.
الدخول لمكتب الكونجريس
It would change his day, all right?
كان يمكن ان يغير هذا يومه، حسناَ؟
That's one thing. Another thing that's for sure
هذا شيء. شيء آخر وهو مؤكد
going to happen is that it will calibrate us.
سوف يحدث انه سوف يقوم بتصحيحنا
We will know that we're not that miracle, right,
سوف نعرف اننا لسنا معجزات
that we're just another duck in a row,
اننا مجرد بطة في صف ما
we're not the only kids on the block, and I think that that's
لسنا الوحيدين في هذا الحيّ, وأعتقد أنه
philosophically a very profound thing to learn.
شيئ عميق جداً لنعلمه, فلسفياً.
We're not a miracle, okay?
لسنا معجزة, حسنا ؟
The third thing that it might tell you is somewhat vague,
الأمر الثالث الذي سنعلمه غامض نوعاً ما,
but I think interesting and important,
ولكنه باعتقادي مثير للإهتمام,
and that is, if you find a signal coming from a more
وهوه أنه إذا عثرت على إشارة قادمة من
advanced society, because they will be,
حضارة متقدمة جداً, لأنهم سيكونون كذلك,
that will tell you something about our own possibilities,
هذا سيبيّن لك شيئاً عن إحتمالاتنا,
that we're not inevitably doomed to self-destruction.
أننا لن ندمّر أنفسنا بالضرورة.
Because they survived their technology,
لأنهم قد نجو مع تقنياتهم,
we could do it too.
و يمكننا نحن فعل ذلك.
Normally when you look out into the universe,
عادة, عندما تنظر الى الكون,
you're looking back in time. All right?
فإنك تنظر الى الماضي, صح؟
That's interesting to cosmologists.
هذا يثير اهتمام علماء الكون
But in this sense, you actually can look into the future,
ولكن بهذه الطريقة, فإنك ستستطيع النظر الى المستقبل,
hazily, but you can look into the future.
بغموض, ولكنك ستنظر الى المستقبل.
So those are all the sorts of things that would come from a detection.
إذاً هذه هي كل الأمور التي قد تحصل بعد التقاط إشارة ما.
Now, let me talk a little bit about something that happens
الآن دعوني أتكلم قليلاً عن شيئ يحدث
even in the meantime, and that is,
في وقتنا الحاضر, وهو,
SETI, I think, is important, because it's exploration, and
أعتقد أن مركز SETI مهم بسبب استكشافاته,
it's not only exploration, it's comprehensible exploration.
وليس فقط "إستكشافات", وإنما الإستكشافات المفهومة.
Now, I gotta tell you, I'm always reading books about
الآن لابدّ أن أقول لكم, أني دائماً أقرأ كتب عن
explorers. I find exploration very interesting,
الإستكشافات. وأجد الإستكشاف جداً مهم,
Arctic exploration, you know, people like Magellan,
اكتشافات القطب الشمالي, كما تعلمون, أشخاص مثل "ماجيللان",
Amundsen, Shackleton, you see Franklin down there,
"آمندسن", "شاكيلتون" كما ترون "فرانكلن" على الشاشة,
Scott, all these guys. It's really nifty, exploration.
"سكوتت", كل هؤلاء الأشخاص. الإستكشاف فعلاً شيئ أنيق.
And they're just doing it because they want to explore,
إنهم يفعلون ذلك فقط لأنهم يريدون أن يكتشفوا,
and you might say, "Oh, that's kind of a frivolous opportunity,"
ستقول : أوه , إنها فرص تافهة"
but that's not frivolous. That's not a frivolous activity,
ولكنها ليست كذلك, إنها ليست نشاطاً عبثياً,
because, I mean, think of ants.
لأنه, أقصد انظروا الى النمل.
You know, most ants are programmed to follow one another
كما تعلمون, كل نملة مبرمجة لكي تلحق بزملاتها
along in a long line, but there are a couple of ants,
جنباً الى جنب في خط طويل, ولكن هناك بعض النملات,
maybe one percent of those ants, that are what they call
ربما 1% من مجموعة النمل, واللذين يُدعَون
pioneer ants, and they're the ones that wander off.
روّاد النمل, وهنّ النملات اللاتي يسرحن لوحدهن.
They're the ones you find on the kitchen countertop.
هؤلاء النملات هم الذن يجدون حافة الطعام ف المطبخ.
You gotta get them with your thumb before they
عليك أن تلتقطها بأصبعك قبل أن
find the sugar or something.
تجد حبة السكر أو شي آخر.
But those ants, even though most of them get wiped out,
ولكن هؤلاء النملات, ومع أن معظمهم يموت,
those ants are the ones that are essential to the survival
هؤلاء وجودهم ضروري لبقاء
of the hive. So exploration is important.
الخلية. لذا فالاستكشافات مهمة.
I also think that exploration is important in terms of
وإني أيضاً أعتقد أنها مهمة من جهة
being able to address what I think is a critical
القدرة على تحديد - الذي أعتقد أنه- نقص حرج
lack in our society, and that is the lack of science literacy,
في مجتمعنا, ألا وهوه الإفتقار لثقافة قراءة العلوم,
the lack of the ability to even understand science.
افتقار حتى للقدرة على فهم العلم.
Now, look, a lot has been written about the
الآن, انظرو, تم كتابة الكثير عن
deplorable state of science literacy in this country.
الوضع البائس للعلوم في هذا البلد.
You've heard about it.
لقد سمعتم عن هذا.
Well, here's one example, in fact.
حسناً, سأعطيكم مثالاً, في الحقيقة
Polls taken, this poll was taken 10 years ago.
استطلاعات للرأي, هذا الاستطلاع تم عمله قبل عشرة أعوام.
It shows like roughly one third of the public thinks
إنه يُظهر أن ثلث الشعب يعتقد
that aliens are not only out there, we're looking for them
أنه لس فقط المخلوقات الفضائية موجودة, نحن نبحث عنهم
out there, but they're here, right?
بل يعتقدون أنهم بيننا !
Sailing the skies in their saucers and occasionally
يبحرون في السماء بصحونهم الطائرة و من وقت لآخر
abducting people for experiments their parents wouldn't approve of.
يختطفون أشخاصاً من أجل القيام بتجارب أهلهم لا يوافقون عليها.
Well, that would be interesting if it was true,
حسناً, هذا سيكون مثيراً لو كان صحيحاً,
and job security for me, but I don't think the evidence is
وأمان وظيفيّ بالنسبة لي, لكن لا أعتقد أن الدليل
very good. That's more, you know, sad than significant.
قويّ. وهذا أمر محزن أكثر كما تعلمون من كونه أمراً كبراً.
But there are other things that people believe
ولكن هناك أمور أخرى يعتقدها الناس
that are significant, like the efficacy of homeopathy,
والتي تعتبر كبيرة, مثل فعالية معالجة المثلية الجنسية !
or that evolution is just, you know, sort of a crazy idea
أو أن التطور هوه فقط عبارة عن فكرة مجنونة
by scientists without any legs, or, you know, evolution,
افتعلها العلماء بدون أي أساس, أو كما تعلمون, التطور ...
all that sort of thing, or global warming.
كل هذه الأمور, أو الإحتباس الحراري.
These sorts of ideas don't really have any validity,
هذا النوع من الأفكار لا يمتلك أي صلاحية,
that you can't trust the scientists.
لا يمكنك الوثوق بالعلماء !.
Now, we've got to solve that problem, because that's
إذا علينا أن نحل هذه المشكلة, لأنها
a critically important problem, and you might say,
مشكلة مهمة وشائكة, ويمكن أن تقول,
"Well, okay, how are we gonna solve that problem with SETI?"
"حسناً, كيف سيحل مركز SETI هذه المشكلة ؟! "
Well, let me suggest to you that SETI obviously can't
حسنا, دعوني أقول لكم أن SETI لن يستطيع بالتأكيد
solve the problem, but it can address the problem.
حل المشكلة, ولكنه يستطيع تحديدها .
It can address the problem by getting young people
يمكنه تحديدها عن طريق جعل الصغار
interested in science. Look, science is hard, it
مهتمين بالعلومن. أنظرو, العلم صعب
has a reputation of being hard, and the facts are, it is hard,
لديه سمعة بكونه صعباً, والحقيقة هي أنه صعب,
and that's the result of 400 years of science, right?
وهذه هي نتيجة 400 عام من العلم. صحيح ؟
I mean, in the 18th century, in the 18th century
أعني, في القرن الثامن عشر
you could become an expert on any field of science
كان بإمكانك أن تكون خبيراً بأي فرع من العلوم
in an afternoon by going to a library,
شي نهار, عن طريق الذهاب إلى مكتبة ما,
if you could find the library, right?
إذا وجدت المكتبة, صح ؟
In the 19th century, if you had a basement lab,
أما في القرن التاسع عشر, إذا كنت تملك مختبراً في قبوِك,
you could make major scientific discoveries
كان بإمكانك اكتشاف أشياء علمية مهمة
in your own home. Right? Because there was all this
في منزلك ! صحيح؟ لأن العلم كان
science just lying around waiting for somebody to pick it up.
في كل مكان ينتظر ليتم اكتشافه.
Now, that's not true anymore.
ولكن الآن هذا لم يعد صحيحاً.
Today, you've got to spend years in grad school
في هذه الأيام, عليك تمضية أعوام في الدراسات العليا
and post-doc positions just to figure out what
ومناصب ما بعد الدكتوراه فقط لكي تعرف
the important questions are.
ماهي الأسئلة المهمة.
It's hard. There's no doubt about it.
أنه صعب, لا شكّ في ذلك.
And in fact, here's an example: the Higgs boson,
وفي الحقيقة, سأعطيكم مثالاً : الهغز بوزون,
finding the Higgs boson.
البحث عن الهغز بوزون.
Ask the next 10 people you see on the streets,
اسأل عشرة أشخاص من الشارع
"Hey, do you think it's worthwhile to spend billions
"هل تعتقدون أنه من المجدي إنفاق الملايين
of Swiss francs looking for the Higgs boson?"
من العملة السويسرية, فقط للبحث عن هيغز بوزون؟ "
And I bet the answer you're going to get, is,
وأراهنك أن الجواب الذي ستحصل عليه هو,
"Well, I don't know what the Higgs boson is,
"حسناً, لا أعلم ما هوه الهيغز بوزون,
and I don't know if it's important."
ولا أعلم إن كان مهماً. "
And probably most of the people wouldn't even know
ومن الممكن أن الأشخاص لن يعلموا حتى
the value of a Swiss franc, okay?
قمة العملة السويسرية, حسنا؟ "
And yet we're spending billions of Swiss francs on this problem.
ولكن مازلنا ننفق بلايين الفرنكات السويسرية على هذه المشكلة.
Okay? So that doesn't get people interested in science
حسنا ؟ إذا هذا لن يجعل العالم يهتمون بالعلوم
because they can't comprehend what it's about.
لأنهم لا ستطيعون فهمه.
SETI, on the other hand, is really simple.
SETI, من نايحة أخرى بسيط جداً.
We're going to use these big antennas and we're going to
سنقوم باستعمال هذه الأنتينات الكبيرة وسنقوم
try to eavesdrop on signals. Everybody can understand that.
بمحاولة التنصت على الإشارات. الكلّ يستطيع استيعاب هذا .
Yes, technologically, it's very sophisticated,
أجل, تقنياً, هذا جداً معقد,
but everybody gets the idea.
ولكن الجميع يفهم الفكرة.
So that's one thing. The other thing is, it's exciting science.
هذا شيئ, والشيئ الآخر هوه أنه علم ممتع.
It's exciting because we're naturally interested
إنه ممتع لأننا طبيعياً مهتمين
in other intelligent beings, and I think that's
بمخلوقات ذكية أخرى, وإني أعتقد أنه
part of our hardwiring.
جزء لا تجزأ من كياننا.
I mean, we're hardwired to be interested
أعني أننا مركّبون لنكون مهتمين
in beings that might be, if you will, competitors,
بمخلوقات قد تكون, إذا صح التعبير, منافسة,
or if you're the romantic sort, possibly even mates. Okay?
أو إن كنت من النوع الرومنسي, فممكن أن تكون هذه المخلوقات أصحاب, اوك ؟
I mean, this is analogous to our interest in things that
أعني, هذا مشابه لاهتمامنا بالأشياء التي
have big teeth. Right?
لديها أسنان كبيرة. صح ؟
We're interested in things that have big teeth, and you
نحن نحبّ الأشياء ذي الأسنان الكبيرة, وانت
can see the evolutionary value of that, and you can also see
تستطيع أن ترى القيمة التطورية لهذا الأمر, ويمكنك أيضاً أن ترى
the practical consequences by watching Animal Planet.
النتائج العملية لمشاهدة قناة "كوكب الحيوان"
You notice they make very few programs about gerbils.
ستلاحظ أنهم يعرضون فقط القليل عن الجرابيع.
It's mostly about things that have big teeth.
معظم ما يعرضونه هوه عن ذوات الأسنان الكبيرة.
Okay, so we're interested in these sorts of things.
حسناً, فنحن مهتمون بهذا النوع من الأشياء.
And not just us. It's also kids.
ولسنا وحدنا فقط ولكن الأطفال أيضاً.
This allows you to pay it forward by using this subject as a
فيمكنك استعمال هذا كمصيدة
hook to science, because SETI involves all kinds of science,
للعلم, لأن SETI يحتوي على جميع أنواع العلوم,
obviously biology, obviously astronomy,
بديهياً, علم الأحياء, وبديهياً علم الكون,
but also geology, also chemistry, various scientific
وأيضاً الجغرافيا, و أيضاً الكيمياء, تخصصات
disciplines all can be presented in the guise of,
علمية متنوعة , كلها تعرض تحت ستار
"We're looking for E.T."
البحث عن المخلوق الفضائي.
So to me this is interesting and important, and in fact,
لذا هذا مثير ومهم بالنسبة لي, وفي الحقيقة,
it's my policy, even though I give a lot of talks to adults,
إنها سياستي, مع أنني أقدم العديد من المحاضرات للكبار,
you give talks to adults, and two days later they're back where they were.
إنك تقدم محاضرة للكبار, وبعد يومين ينسون ويعودون إلى حيث كانو.
But if you give talks to kids, you know,
لكن إذا قدمتها للصغار, كما تعلمون,
one in 50 of them, some light bulb goes off, and they think,
واحد من أصل 50 منهم, ستشعل لمبة ف دماغهم, ويسفكّرون,
"Gee, I'd never thought of that," and then they go,
"ياإلاهي, لم أفكّر يوماً في هذا " ومن ثم يذهبون,
you know, read a book or a magazine or whatever.
ليقرأوا كتاباً أو مجلة أو أ شيئ.
They get interested in something.
يصبحون مهتمين بشيئ.
Now it's my theory, supported only by anecdotal,
هذه نظريتي, مدعومة بأقوالي,
personal anecdotal evidence, but nonetheless,
أدلة وأقوال شخصية, ولكن مع ذلك,
that kids get interested in something between the ages
هؤلاء الأطفال يصبحون مهتمين بشيئ بين عمر
of eight and 11. You've got to get them there.
الثامنة وال11, عليك أن تؤثر عليهم في هذا العمر.
So, all right, I give talks to adults, that's fine, but I try
طب حسناً, إني أعطي محاضرات لبالغين, هذا جيد, ولكني أحاول
and make 10 percent of the talks that I give,
أن أجعل 10% من محاضراتي التي أعطيها,
I try and make those for kids.
أحاول أن أقدمها للصغار.
I remember when a guy came to our high school, actually,
أتذكر عندما أتى شخص إلى مدرستي الثانوية, لا لقد..
it was actually my junior high school. I was in sixth grade.
لقد كانت الإعدادية في الحقيقة, لقد كنت في الصف السادس.
And he gave some talk. All I remember from it
وقد أعطى محاضرة. ولم أتذكر منها
was one word: electronics.
سوى كلمة "إلكترونيات" !.
It was like Dustin Hoffman in "The Graduate," right,
مثل (دستن هوففمان) في فيلم the graduate , صح ؟
when he said "plastics," whatever that means, plastics.
عندما يقول "بلاستيك", مهما كان معناها, بلاستيك.
All right, so the guy said electronics. I don't remember
إذاً, فهذا الشخص قال "إلكترونات", ولا أتذكر
anything else. In fact, I don't remember anything
أي شيئ آخر. في الحقيقة, إني لا أتذكر شيئ
that my sixth grade teacher said all year,
مما علمني إياه معلمي في الصف السادس,
but I remember electronics.
ولكن أتذكر "إلكترونيات".
And so I got interested in electronics, and you know,
لذا أصبحت مهتما بالإلكترونات,
I studied to get my ham license. I was wiring up stuff.
فدرست لأحصل على الشهادة. وقد كنت أكتب أشيائاً.
Here I am at about 15 or something, doing that sort of stuff.
ها أنا في عمر ال15 أو ما شابه, أفعل هذه الأمور.
Okay? That had a big effect on me.
حسنا؟ لقد كان لهذا تأثير كبر عليّ.
So that's my point, that you can have a big effect
لذا هذه هي فكرتي, أنه يمكنك التأثير بشكل كبير
on these kids.
على هؤلاء الأطفال.
In fact, this reminds me, I don't know, a couple years ago
في الحقيقة هذا يذكرني, لا أعلم, من كم سنة مضت
I gave a talk at a school in Palo Alto
قدمت محاضرة لمدرسة في "بولو آلتو"
where there were about a dozen 11-year-olds
وقد كان هناك قرابة ال12 طفلاً أعمارهم 11 سنة.
that had come to this talk.
قد أتوا لحضوري.
I had been brought in to talk to these kids for an hour.
لقد كنت قد أتيت لأتكلم لهؤلاء الأطفال لمدة ساعة..
Eleven-year-olds, they're all sitting in a little semi-circle
11 سنة, كلهم جالسون في حلقة
looking up at me with big eyes, and I started,
ينظرون إلي بأعينهم الكبيرة, وبدأت,
there was a white board behind me, and I started off
لقد كان هناك لوحا أبيض ورائي, وقد بدأت
by writing a one with 22 zeroes after it, and I said,
بكتابة رقم واحد وبعده 22 صفراً, وقلت
"All right, now look, this is the number of stars
"حسنا, انظروا, هذا هوه عدد النجوم
in the visible universe, and this number is so big
في الكون الذي نراه, وهذا الرقم كبير جدا
there's not even a name for it."
حتى أنه لا يوجد أسم له"
And one of these kids shot up his hand, and he said,
أحد الأطفال رفع يده, وقال :
"Well, actually there is a name for it.
"ولكن هناك إسم لهذا الرقم !.
It's a sextra-quadra-hexa-something or other." Right?
إنه سيكسترا-كوارتا-هكسا شيئ من هذا القبيل. "
Now, that kid was wrong by four orders of magnitude,
هذا الطفل كان خاطئا بأربع مستويات تقديرية,
but there was no doubt about it, these kids were smart.
ولكن لم يكن هناك مجال للشك, إن هؤلاء الأطفال أذكياء.
Okay? So I stopped giving the lecture.
حسنا؟ لذا توقفت عن إعطاء المحاضرة.
All they wanted to do was ask questions.
وكل ما كانوا يريدونه هوه إعطائي أسئلة.
In fact, my last comments to these kids, at the end I said,
في الحقيقة, آخر تعليق لي عليهم عندما انتهيت, قلت :
"You know, you kids are smarter
"أن تعلمون أيها الأولاد أنكم أذكى
than the people I work with." Now — (Laughter)
من الأشخاص الذين أعمل معهم." (ضحك)
They didn't even care about that.
لم يهتموا حتى لهذا .
What they wanted was my email address
لقد طلبوا بريدي الإلكتروني
so they could ask me more questions. (Laughter)
لكي يبعثوا لي بالمزيد من الأسئلة. (ضحك)
Let me just say, look, my job is a privilege
دعوني أقول, انظروا, إن عملي ميزة
because we're in a special time.
لأننا في زمن مميز.
Previous generations couldn't do this experiment at all.
الأجيال السابقة لم يكن بمقدورها القيام بهذه التجارب.
In another generation down the line,
ومع جيل جديد لاحق,
I think we will have succeeded.
أعتقد أننا سنكون قد نجحنا.
So to me, it is a privilege, and when I look in the mirror,
لذا إنه عمل مميز, وعندما أنظر لنفسي بالمرآة,
the facts are that I really don't see myself.
إنني حقاً لا أرى نفسي.
What I see is the generation behind me.
الذي أراه هوه الأجيال القادمة.
These are some kids from the Huff School, fourth graders.
هؤلاء بعض الأطفال من مدرسة "هافف" في الصف الرابع.
I talked there, what, two weeks ago, something like that.
كنت هناك منذ قرابة إسبوعين .
I think that if you can instill some interest in science
أعتقد أنك إن استطعت غرس الإهتمام بالعلم
and how it works, well, that's a payoff
وكيفية عمله, فهذه مكافئة
beyond easy measure. Thank you very much.
فوق الإعتياد, شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
تصفيق